{"tossups": [{"question": "Three of this civilization\u2019s most powerful women - Lady Xoc [Shok], Lady Sak \u2018uk, and Lady Kan Ik- were related to the longest-ruling king of Palenque [puh-LEN-kay], Pacal the Great. This civilization\u2019s religion involved sacrifices of food, animals, and humans to multiple gods, including Ixchel [ee-SHELL], Itzamna, and the Moon Goddess. Women traditionally wore the<em> huipil</em> [WEE-peel] in, for the point, what Mesoamerican civilization known for its calendar?", "answer": "<b> Maya</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "Trees of this resource sacred to Poseidon known as<em> Moria</em> were found throughout Attica. Thales, one of the Seven Wise Men of Greece, created what may have been the world\u2019s first monopoly by hoarding presses to process this fruit. Legend has it that the Athenians chose Athena to be their patron after she gave them a tree that produced this natural resource. For the point, name this Mediterranean fruit used to make a namesake oil.", "answer": "<b> Olive</b>s (accept<b> Olive</b> Oil)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s troops attempted to stay in Siberia after coalition forces left during the Russian Civil War in a failed attempt to create a Far East buffer state. This ruler\u2019s cabinet received and promptly ignored the Hull Note suggesting they withdraw forces from French Indochina and China. This ruler surrendered during the Jewel Voice Broadcast following the bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki. For the point, name this Japanese Emperor throughout World War Two.", "answer": "<b> Hirohito</b> (accept<b> Showa</b> Emperor)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This ongoing work began at seven papers on October 2, 1950, including its creator\u2019s hometown paper, the<em> Minneapolis Tribune</em>. Over almost 50 years of syndication and nearly 18 thousand strips, this creation was a bastion of inclusiveness with characters including a fully-accepted African-American student named Franklin and a confident, athletic girl named Patty. For the point, name this creation of Charles Schulz featuring Charlie Brown and his dog, Snoopy.", "answer": "<em><b> Peanuts</b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "Nazi collaborators in this nation known as the Arajs [uh-RAZH] Kommando committed the second largest massacre of World War Two in the Rumbula Forest. Lothar Rendulic led the isolated Army Group Courland that held out in this nation until Germany\u2019s surrender in 1945. Along with its northern and southern neighbors, this country participated in the anti-Communist Singing Revolution in 1988. For the point, name this Baltic state with its capital at Riga", "answer": "Republic of<b> Latvia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man adapted Diophantus\u2019s concept of \u201cadequality\u201d in his interpretation of infinitesimal calculus. During his time as a lawyer, this man defended a priest who hid an escapee from a Calvinist re-education school. This mathematician struck up a correspondence with Blaise Pascal that formed the basis of probability. This mathematician claimed that the margins of his book were too small to contain a\u201cmarvellous\u201d proof for one of his theorems that went unproven for nearly 460 years. For the point, name this scientist whose \u201cLast Theorem\u201d was finally proven in 1995 by Andrew Wiles.", "answer": "Pierre de<b> Fermat</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One leader of this nation was advised by a group of economists known as the \u201cBerkeley Mafia\u201d and followed the Pancasila ideology. A massacre of demonstrators seeking independence from this country occurred in a graveyard in Dili during this country\u2019s occupation of East Timor. The policy of \u201cGuided Democracy\u201d was implemented by the first president of this nation, Sukarno. For the point, name this Asian nation that contains the islands of Bali and Java.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Indonesia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This deity turned Lyncus into a lynx after he tried to murder their disciple Triptolemus. This deity is the older of the two subjects of the Eleusinian Mysteries cult. This deity cursed Erysichthon to become so hungry that he ate himself. This deity brought eternal winter after her child was tricked into eating pomegranate seeds. For the point, name this Greek goddess of agriculture whose daughter Persephone lives in the underworld with Hades.", "answer": "<b> Demeter</b> (accept<b> Ceres</b> before \u201cEleusinian\u201d)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "A poem set during this conflict envisions \u201cA voice in the darkness, a knock at the door, and a word that shall echo forevermore!\u201d Poems like \u201cThe Indian Burying Ground\u201d and \u201cThe Wild Honeysuckle\u201dwere written by the so-called poet of this war, Philip Freneau. A poem set during this war opens, \u201cListen my children, and you shall hear\u201d and tells of a hero who uses a light in the North Church tower as a signal. For the point, name this war, the setting of Longfellow\u2019s \u201cPaul Revere\u2019s Ride.\u201d", "answer": "<b> American Revolution</b> (accept<b> Revolutionary</b> War)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Jaqueline du Pr\u00b4e popularized Edward Elgar\u2019s concerto in E-minor for this instrument, the earliest surviving examples of which were made by celebrated luthier, Andrea Amati. Derek Simpson was featured playing this instrument on The Beatles\u2019s \u201cStrawberry Fields Forever,\u201d and Antonio Stradivari is credited with standardizing its size as somewhat smaller than a bass violin. For the point, name this stringed instrument played by Yo-Yo Ma, the largest instrument in a string quartet.", "answer": "Violon<b>cello</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "An extinct subset from the same genus as these domesticated animals named hueques were used by the Mapuche on the island of Mocha [MOTE-sha]. On Lake Maracucha, archaeologists found maize 10,000 feet above sea level brought by herds of this mammal. A relative of the god Inti named Urcuchillay was believed to be one of these camelids, which is one of two members of its genus, along with the guanaco. For the point, name this beast of burden used by Pre-Columbian societies like the Inca.", "answer": "<b> Llama</b> (do not accept Alpaca or Guanaco. Editor\u2019s note: Guanaco were not domesticated.)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 1967, Kathrine Switzer became the first woman to officially participate in this event, finishing the competition despite Jock Semple\u2019s assaults. This event was scheduled, as usual, on Patriot\u2019s Day in 2020 but was postponed, then cancelled, due to COVID-19, the first cancellation in its 124 year history. The Tsarnaev [sar-NYE-ev] brothers killed three people in a bombing at the 2013 running of, for the point, what annual long-distance race held in Massachusetts?", "answer": "<b> Boston Marathon</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "A village in this mountain range provided the site for the Hallstatt culture which preceded the La Tene culture here. Base tunnels in this mountain range have connected Uri and Ticino and decreased train travel times between other cantons as well. For the point, name this range in which the Romansch language has survived near St. Moritz in Switzerland.", "answer": "<b> Alps</b> (accept<b> Pennine Alps</b> before Halstatt)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The name of these places applied to both the places themselves as well as the governing body that controlled them. Millions of people were allowed to leave these places during the \u201cGreat Thaw.\u201d Article 58 was used in the 1920s and 30s to imprison innocent people in these places, and Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn wrote a three-volume book on these places. For the point, name this system of forced labor camps in the former Soviet Union.", "answer": "<b> Gulag</b>s (prompt on prison camps, Soviet labor camps, or similar answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A decree that gave Jews in this former French colony European citizenship is named for the head of the Alliance Isra`elite Universelle, Adolphe Cr\u00b4emieux. The<em> Front de Lib\u00b4eration Nationale</em> of this nation signed the Evian Accords with Charles de Gaulle in 1962. That ended an eight-year war of independence in this nation whose native supporters of the French were called \u201cPied-Noir.\u201d For the point, name this nation which since 2011 has been the largest on the continent of Africa.", "answer": "People\u2019s Democratic Republic of<b> Algeria</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "During a scandal named for this good, Orville Babcock purchased land in Florida using money he received from John McDonald. During that scandal, participants tried to skirt taxes on this good during the Grant administration. The Watermelon Army under Light-Horse Harry Lee suppressed a revolt named for this good, which was sparked by an excise tax issued by Alexander Hamilton. A 1791 rebellion in Western Pennsylvania takes its name from, for the point, what alcoholic beverage?", "answer": "<b> Whiskey</b> (accept<b> Whiskey</b> Rebellion or<b> Whiskey</b> Ring scandal)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The conquests of this city and of Yerevan were the subjects of two kiosks built in the Topkapi Palace in Istanbul by Sultan Murat III. This city, built northwest of the ruins of Ctesiphon [TESS-if-on], the Sassanid capital, had its Golden Gate Palace sponsored by its ruler Al-Mansur. The refusal to pay tribute led to Hulagu Khan sacking this city, burning its House of Wisdom, and leaving the Abbasid Caliphate in disarray. For the point, name this modern capital of Iraq.", "answer": "<b> Baghdad</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In one speech, this leader protested \u201cthis high-handed outrage upon my citizen\u2019s rights.\u201d This leader introduced a resolution to create the AERA, which split into wings led separately by this leader and Lucy Stone over the 15th Amendment. Justice Ward Hunt fined this leader $100 for voting in the U.S. presidential election of 1872. For the point, name this woman who founded the National American Woman Suffrage Association with Elizabeth Cady Stanton.", "answer": "Susan B.<b> Anthony</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}